looked like. Chapter 7 Queer Lodgings The next morning Bilbo woke up with the
early sun in his eyes. He jumped up to
look at the time and to go and put his
kettle on and found he was not home at all. So he sat down and wished in vain
for a wash and a brush. He did not get either nor tea nor toast nor bacon for
his breakfast, only cold mutton and rapid. And after that he had to get
ready for a fresh start. This time he was allowed to climb onto an eagle's
back and cling between his wings. The air rushed over him and he shut his
eyes. The dwarves were crying farewells and promising to repay the Lord of the
eagles if ever they could, as off rose 15 great birds from the mountain side.
The sun was still close to the eastern edge of things. The morning was cool,
and mists were in the valleys and hollows and twined here and there about
the peaks and pinnacles of the hills.
Bilbo opened an eye to peep and saw that the birds were already high up and the
world was far away and the mountains were falling back behind them into the
distance. He shut his eyes again and held on tighter. Don't pinch, said his
eagle. Ye need not be frightened like a rabbit, even if you look rather like
one. It is a fair morning with little wind.
What is finer than flying? Bilbo would have liked to say a warm bath and late
breakfast on the lawn afterwards, but he thought it better to say nothing at all,
and to let go his clutch just a tiny bit. After a good while the eagles must
have seen the point they were making for, even from their great height, for
they began to go down, circling round in great spirals.
They did this for a long while, and at last the hobbit opened his eyes again.
The earth was much nearer, and below them were trees that looked like oaks
and elms, and wide grasslands, and a river running through it all. But
cropping out of the ground, right in the path of the stream, which looped itself
about it, was a great rock, almost a hill of stone, like a last outpost of
the distant mountains, or a huge piece cast miles into the plain by some giant among giants.
Quickly now to the top of this rock. The eagles swooped one by one and set down
their passengers.
Farewell, they cried, wherever you fare, till your IE receive you at the journeys
end. That is the polite thing to say among eagles.
May the wind under your wings bear you where the sun sails and the moon walks,
answered Gandalf, who knew the correct reply.
And so they parted. And though the lord of the eagles became in after days the
king of all birds and wore a golden crown, and his 15 chieftains golden
collars made of the gold that the dwarves gave them, Bilbo never saw them
again except high and far off in the battle of five armies. But as that comes
in at the end of this tale, we will say
no more about it just now. There was a flat space on the top of the hill of
stone, and a well-worn path with many steps leading down it to the river,
across which a ford of huge flat stones led to the grassland beyond the stream.
There was a little cave, a wholesome one, with a pebbly floor, at the foot of
the steps, and near the end of the stony ford. Here the party gathered and
discussed what was to be done.
I always meant to see you all safe, if possible, over the mountains, said the
wizard, and now, by good management and good luck, I have done it. Indeed, we
are now a good deal further east than I ever meant to come with you, for after
all this is not my adventure. I may look in on it again before it is all over,
but in the meanwhile, I have some other pressing business to attend to." The
dwarves groaned and looked most distressed, and Bilbo wept. They had
begun to think Gandalf was going to come all the way and would always be there to
help them out of difficulties. "I am not going to disappear this very instant,"
said he. "I can give you a day or two more. Probably I can help you out of
your present plight, and I need a little help myself. We have no food and no
baggage and no ponies to ride, and you don't know where you are. Now I can tell
you that you are still some miles north of the path which we should have been
following if we had not left the mountain pass in a hurry.
Very few people live in these parts unless they have come here since I was
last down this way which is some years ago.
But there is somebody that I know of who lives not far away that somebody made
the steps on the great rock the Kok. I believe he calls it. He does not come
here often, certainly not in the daytime, and it is no good waiting for
him. In fact, it would be very dangerous. We must go and find him, and
if all goes well at our meeting, I think I shall be off and wish you like the
eagle's farewell wherever you fare."
They begged him not to leave them. They offered him dragon gold and silver and
jewels, but he would not change his mind. We shall see. We shall see, he
said, and I think I have earned already some of your dragon gold when you have
got it. After that they stopped pleading. Then they took off their
clothes and bathed in the river, which was shallow and clear and stony at the
ford and stony at the ford. When they had dried in the sun, which was now
strong and warm, they were refreshed, if still sore, and a little hungry. Soon
they crossed the ford carrying the hobbit and then began to march through
the long green grass and down the lines of the wide-armed oaks and the tall
elms. And why is it called the carac?
asked Bilbo as he went along at the wizard's side. He called it the Karac
because carac is his word for it. He calls things like that karax. And this
one is the karac because it is the only one near his home and he knows it well.
Who calls it? Who knows it? The somebody I spoke of, a very great person. You
must all be very polite when I introduce you. I shall introduce you slowly, two
by two, I think, and you must be careful not to annoy him, or heaven knows what
will happen. He can be appalling when he is angry, though he is kind enough if humored.
Still, I warn you, he gets angry easily.
The dwarves all gathered round when they heard the wizard talking like this to
Bilbo. Is that the person you are taking us to now? They asked. Couldn't you find
someone more easytempered? Hadn't you better explain it all a bit clearer and
so on? Yes, it certainly is. No, I could not, and I was explaining very
carefully, answered the wizard crossly.
If you must know more, his name is Bejorn. He is very strong and he is a
skin changer. What a furer, a man that calls rabbits conies when he doesn't
turn their skins into squirrels? asked Bilbo.
Good gracious heavens. No, no, no, said Gandalf. Don't be a fool, Mr. Baggins,
if you can help it, and in the name of all wonder, don't mention the word frier
again as long as you are within a 100 miles of his house. nor rug, cape,
tippet, muff, nor any other such unfortunate word. He is a skin changer.
He changes his skin. Sometimes he is a huge black bear. Sometimes he is a
great, strong, black-haired man with huge arms and a great beard.
I cannot tell you much more, though that ought to be enough. Some say that he is
a bear descended from the great and ancient bears of the mountains that
lived there before the giants came.
Others say that he is a man descended from the first men who lived before Smal
or the other dragons came into this part of the world and before the goblins came
into the hills out of the north. I cannot say though I fancy the last is
the true tale. He is not the sort of person to ask questions of. At any rate,
he is under no enchantment but his own.
He lives in an oak wood and has a great wooden house, and as a man, he keeps
cattle and horses, which are nearly as marvelous as himself. They work for him
and talk to him. He does not eat them, neither does he hunt or eat wild
animals. He keeps hives and hives of great fierce bees, and lives most on
cream and honey. As a bear, he ranges far and wide. I once saw him sitting all
alone on the top of the car at night, watching the moon sinking towards the
misty mountains, and I heard him growl in the tongue of bears. The day will
come when they will perish, and I shall go back. That is why I believe he once
came from the mountains himself. Bilbo and the dwarves had now plenty to think
about, and they asked no more questions.
They still had a long way to walk before them. Ups slope and down dale they
plotted. It grew very hot. Sometimes they rested under the trees, and then
Bilbo felt so hungry that he would have eaten acorns, if any, had been ripe
enough yet to have fallen to the ground.
It was the middle of the afternoon before they noticed that great patches
of flowers had begun to spring up, all the same kinds growing together as if
they had been planted. Especially there was clover waving patches of cockcomb
clover and purple clover and wide stretches of short white sweet
honeysmelling clover. There was a buzzing and a worring and a droning in
the air. Bees were busy everywhere. And such bees. Bilbo had never seen anything
like them. If one was to sting me, he thought I should swell up as big again
as I am. They were bigger than hornets.
The drones were bigger than your thumb a good deal, and the bands of yellow on
their deep black bodies shone like fiery gold. "We are getting near," said
Gandalf. "We are on the edge of his bee pastures. After a while they came to a
belt of tall and very ancient oaks, and beyond these to a high thorn hedge
through which you could neither see nor scramble." You would better wait here,
said the wizard to the dwarves, and when I call or whistle, begin to come after
me. You will see the way I go, but only in pairs, mind, about 5 minutes between
each pair of you. Bomb is fattest and will do for two. He had better come
alone and last. Come on, Mr. Baggins.
There is a gate somewhere around this way. And with that, he went off along
the hedge, taking the frightened hobbit with him. They soon came to a wooden
gate high and broad beyond which they could see gardens and a cluster of low
wooden buildings, some thatched and made of unshaped logs, barns, stables, sheds,
and a long low wooden house. Inside, on the southward side of the great hedge
were rows and rows of hives with bell-shaped tops made of straw. The
noise of the giant bees flying to and fro and crawling in and out filled all
the air. The wizard and the hobbit pushed open the heavy creaking gate and
went down a wide track towards the house. Some horses, very sleek and
well-groomed, trotted up across the grass and looked at them intently with
very intelligent faces. Then off they galloped to the buildings. "They have
gone to tell him of the arrival of strangers," said Gandalf.
Soon they reached a courtyard, three walls of which were formed by the wooden
house and its two long wings. In the middle there was lying a great oak trunk
with many lpped branches beside it.
Standing near was a huge man with a thick black beard and hair and great
bare arms and legs with knotted muscles.
He was clothed in a tunic of wool down to his knees and was leaning on a large
axe. The horses were standing by him with their noses at his shoulder. "Ah,
here they are," he said to the horses.
"They don't look dangerous. You can be off." He laughed a great rolling laugh,
put down his ax, and came forward. "Who are you, and what do you want?" he asked
gruffly, standing in front of them, and towering tall above Gandalf. As for
Bilbo, he could easily have trotted through his legs without ducking his
head to miss the fringe of the man's brown tunic. I am Gandalf, said the
wizard. Never heard of him, growled the man. And what's this little fellow? He
said, stooping down to frown at the hobbit with his bushy black eyebrows.
That is Mr. Baggins. A hobbit of good family and unimpeachable reputation,
said Gandalf. Bilbo bowed. He had no hat to take off and was painfully conscious
of his many missing buttons. I am a wizard, continued Gandalf. I have heard
of you, if you have not heard of me, but perhaps you have heard of me, but
perhaps you have heard of my good cousin Ratagast, who lives near the southern
borders of Murkwood.
Yes, not a bad fellow as wizards go, I believe. I used to see him now and
again, said Bejorn. Well, now I know who you are, or who you say you are. What do
you want? To tell you the truth, we have lost our luggage and nearly lost our
way, and are rather in need of help, or at least of advice. I may say, we have
had rather a bad time with goblins in the mountains." "Goblins?" said the big
man less gruffly. "Oh ho, so you've been having trouble with them, have you? What
did you go near them for?" We did not mean to. They surprised us at night in a
pass which we had to cross. We were coming out of the lands over west into these countries.
It is a long tale. "Then you had better come inside and tell me some of it, if
it won't take all day," said the man, leading the way through a dark door that
opened out of the courtyard into the house. Following him, they found
themselves in a wide hall with a fireplace in the middle. Though it was
summer, there was a wood fire burning, and the smoke was rising to the
blackened rafters in search of the way out through an opening in the roof. They
passed through this dim hall, lit only by the fire and the hole above it, and
came through another smaller door into a sort of veranda, propped on wooden posts
made of single tree trunks. It faced south and was still warm and filled with
the light of the westering sun which slanted into it and fell golden on the
garden full of flowers that came right up to the steps. Here they sat on wooden
benches while Gandalf began his tail and Bilbo swung his dangling legs and looked
at the flowers in the garden, wondering what their names could be, as he had
never seen half of them before. "I was coming over the mountains with a friend
or two," said the wizard. or two. I can only see one and a little one at that,
said Beerren. Well, to tell you the truth, I did not like to bother you with
a lot of us until I found out if you were busy.
I will give a call if I may. Go on, call away." So Gandalf gave a long shrill
whistle, and presently Thoren and Dory came round the house by the garden path
and stood bowing low before them. One or three? You meant I see, said Beerren.
But these aren't hobbits. They are dwarves.
Thor and Oaken Shield at your service.
Dory, at your service, said the two dwarves, bowing again. I don't need your
service. Thank you, said Beerren. But I expect you need mine. I am not over fond
of dwarves. But if it is true you are Thoren, son of Thra, son of Thor, I
believe, and that your companion is respectable, and that you are enemies of
goblins, and are not up to any mischief in my lands. What are you up to, by the
way? They are on their way to visit the land of their fathers, away east beyond
Mirkwood, put in Gandalf, and it is entirely an accident that we
are in your lands at all. We were crossing by the high pass that should
have brought us to the road that lies to the south of your country when we were
attacked by the evil goblins as I was about to tell you. Go on telling then,
said Beerren, who was never very polite.
There was a terrible storm. The stone giants were out hurling rocks, and at
the head of the pass we took refuge in a cave, the hobbit and I and several of
our companions.
Do you call two several? Well, no. As a matter of fact, there were more than
two. Where are they? Killed, eaten, gone home. Well, no. They don't seem ought to
have come when I whistled. Shy, I expect. You see, we are very much afraid
that we are rather a lot for you to entertain.
Go on. Whistle again. I am in for a party it seems and one or two more won't
make much difference growled Bjorn.
Gandalf whistled again but Nori and Aie were there almost before he had stopped
for if you remember Gandalf had told them to come in pairs every 5 minutes.
Hello said Beern. You came pretty quick.
Where were you hiding? Come on my Jack in the boxes.
Nori at your service or at? They began, but Beerren interrupted them. Thank you.
When I want your help, I will ask for it. Sit down and let's get on with this
tale, or it will be supper time before it is ended. As soon as we were asleep,
went on Gandalf, a crack at the back of the cave opened. Goblins came out and
grabbed the hobbit and the dwarves in our troop of ponies.
Troop of ponies? What were you a traveling circus? Or were you carrying
lots of goods? Or do you always call six a troop? Oh, no. As a matter of fact,
there were more than six ponies, for there were more than six of us, and
well, here are two more. Just at that moment, Balon and Dwallan appeared and
bowed so low that their beards swept the stone floor. The big man was frowning at
first, but they did their best to be frightfully polite and kept on nodding
and bending and bowing and waving their hoods before their knees in proper dwarf
fashion till he stopped frowning and burst into a chuckling laugh. They looked so comical.
Troop was right, he said. A fine comic one. Come in my merry men and what are
your names? I don't want your service just now, only your names. and then sit
down and stop wagging. "Balon and Dwellan," they said, not daring to be
offended, and sat flop on the floor, looking rather surprised. "Now go on
again," said Beerren to the wizard.
"Where was I?" "Oh, yes, I was not grasped. I killed a goblin or two with a
flash." "Good," growled Bejorn. "It is some good being a wizard, then." And
slipped inside the crack before it closed. I followed down into the main
hall, which was crowded with goblins.
The great goblin was there with 30 or 40 armed guards. I thought to myself, even
if they were not all chained together, what can a dozen do against so many?
A dozen? That's the first time I've heard eight called a dozen. Or have you
still got some more jacks that haven't yet come out of their boxes?
Well, yes, there seem to be a couple more here now. Phy and Killy, I believe,
said Gandalf, as these two now appeared and stood smiling and bowing.
That's enough, said Beerren. Sit down and be quiet now. Go on, Gandalf. So
Gandalf went on with the tale until he came to the fight in the dark, the
discovery of the lower gate, and their horror when they found that Mr. Baggins
had been mislaid. We counted ourselves and found that there was no hobbit.
There were only 14 of us left.
14? That's the first time I've heard one from 10. Leave 14? You mean nine? Or
else you haven't told me yet all the names of your party. Well, of course you
haven't seen on and glowing yet. And bless me, here they are. I hope you will
forgive them for bothering you. Oh, let them all come. Hurry up. Come along, you
two, and sit down. But look here, Gandalf. Even now, we have only got
yourself and 10 dwarves and the hobbit that was lost. That only makes 11 + one
mislaid, and not 14, unless wizards count differently to other people. But
now, please get on with the tale. Bejorn did not show it more than he could help,
but really he had begun to get very interested. You see, in the old days, he
had known the very part of the mountains that Gandalf was describing. He nodded
and he growled when he heard of the hobbit's reappearance and of their
scramble down the stone slide and of the wolf ring in the woods. When Gandalf
came to their climbing into trees with the wolves all underneath, he got up and
stroed about and muttered, "I wish I had been there. I would have given them more
than fireworks."
"Well," said Gandalf very glad to see that his tail was making a good
impression. I did the best I could.
There we were with the wolves going mad underneath us and the forest beginning
to blaze in places when the goblins came down from the hills and discovered us.
They yelled with delight and sang songs making fun of us. 15 birds in five fur
trees. Good heavens growled. Don't pretend that goblins can't count. They
can. 12 isn't 15 and they know it. And so do I. There were Befer and Bofur as
well. I haven't ventured to introduce them before, but here they are. In came
Beef and Bofur, and me, gasped Bomber, puffing up behind. He was fat and also
angry at being left till last. He refused to wait 5 minutes, and followed
immediately after the other two. Well, now there are 15 of you, and since
goblins can count, I suppose that is all that there were up the trees. Now
perhaps we can finish this story without any more interruptions.
Mr. Baggin saw then how clever Gandalf had been.
The interruptions had really made Bejorn more interested in the story, and the
story had kept him from sending the dwarves off at once like suspicious
beggars. He never invited people into his house, if he could help it. He had
very few friends, and they lived a good way away, and he never invited more than
a couple of these to his house at a time.
Now he had got 15 strangers sitting in his porch. By the time the wizard had
finished his tale, and had told of the eagle's rescue, and of how they had all
been brought to the Karac, the sun had fallen behind the peaks of the Misty
Mountains, and the shadows were long in Bejorn's garden. "A very good tale,"
said he, "the best I have heard for a long while. If all beggars could tell
such a good one, they might find me kinder. You may be making it all up, of
course, but you deserve a supper for the story all the same. Let's have something to eat.
Yes, please, they all said together.
Thank you very much. Inside the hall, it was now quite dark. Beern clapped his
hands, and in trotted four beautiful white ponies, and several large,
long-bodied gray dogs. Bejorn said something to them in a queer language,
like animal noises, turned into talk.
They went out again and soon came back carrying torches in their mouths, which
they lit at the fire and stuck in low brackets on the pillars of the hall
about the central hearth. The dogs could stand on their hind legs when they
wished, and carry things with their forefe. Quickly they got outboards and
trestles from the sidewalls and set them up near the fire. Then Baba was heard,
and in came some snow white sheep led by a large cold black ram. One bore a white
cloth embroidered at the edges with figures of animals. Others bore on their
broadbacks trays with bowls and platters and knives and wooden spoons which the
dogs took and quickly laid on the trestle tables. These were very low, low
enough even for Bilbo to sit at comfortably. Beside them, a pony pushed
two low-seated benches with wide rush bottoms and little short, thick legs for
Gandalf and Thoren, while at the far end he put Beern's big black chair of the
same sort in which he sat with his great legs stuck far out under the table.
These were all the chairs he had in his hole, and he probably had them low like
the tables for the convenience of the wonderful animals that waited on him.
What did the rest sit on? They were not forgotten. The other ponies came in
rolling round drum-shaped sections of logs, smoothed and polished, and low
enough even for Bilbo. So soon they were all seated at Beern's table, and the
hall had not seen such a gathering for many a year. There they had a supper or
a dinner, such as they had not had since they left the last homely house in the
west, and said goodbye to Eland.
The light of the torches and the fire flickered about them, and on the table
were two tall red beeswax candles. All the time they ate, Beer, in his deep
rolling voice told tales of the wild lands on this side of the mountains, and
especially of the dark and dangerous wood that lay outstretched far to north
and south, a day's ride before them, barring their way to the east, the
terrible forest of Murkwood.
The dwarves listened and shook their beards, for they knew that they must
soon venture into that forest, and that after the mountains it was the worst of
the perils they had to pass before they came to the dragon's stronghold.
When dinner was over, they began to tell tales of their own, but Bejorn seemed to
be growing drowsy and paid little heed to them. They spoke most of gold and
silver and jewels and the making of things by Smithcraft, and Bejorn did not
appear to care for such things. There were no things of gold or silver in his
hall, and few, save the knives were made of metal at all. They sat long at the
table with their wooden drinking bowls filled with me. The dark night came on
outside. The fires in the middle of the hall were built with fresh logs, and the
torches were put out, and still they sat in the light of the dancing flames, with
the pillars of the house standing tall behind them, and dark at the top like
trees of the forest. Whether it was magic or not, it seemed to Bilbo that he
heard a sound like wind in the branches, stirring in the rafters, and the hoot of
owls. Soon he began to nod with sleep, and the voices seemed to grow far away
until he woke with a start. The great door had creaked and slammed. Beern was
gone. The dwarves were sitting cross-legged on the floor around the
fire, and presently they began to sing.
Some of the verses were like this, but there were many more, and their singing
went on for a long while. The wind was on the withered heath, but in the forest
stirred no leaf. Their shadows lay by night and day, and dark things silent
crept beneath. The wind came down from mountains cold, and like a tide it
roared and rolled. The branches groaned, the forest moaned, and leaves were laid
upon the mold. The wind went on from west to east. All movement in the forest
ceased, but shrill and hush across the marsh, its whistling voices were
released. The grasses hissed, their tassels bent, the reeds were rattling on
it went all shaken pool under heaven's cool, where racing clouds were torn and
rent. It passed the lonely mountain bear and swept above the dragon's lair. Their
black and dark lay boulders stark and flying smoke was in the air. It left the
world and took its flight over the wide seas of the night. The moon set sail
upon the gale, and stars were fanned to leaping light. Bilbo began to nod again.
Suddenly upst Gandalf.
It is time for us to sleep, he said. For us, but not, I think, for Bejorn. In
this hall, we can rest sound and safe.
But I warn you all not to forget what Bejorn said before he left us. You must
not stray outside until the sun is up on your peril. Bilbo found that beds had
already been laid at the side of the hall on a sort of raised platform
between the pillars and the outer wall.
For him there was a little mattress of straw and wool and blankets. He snuggled
into them very gladly. Summertime though it was. The fire burned low and he fell
asleep. Yet in the night he woke, the fire had now sunk to a few embers. The
dwarves and Gandalf, for all asleep, to judge by their breathing. A splash of
white on the floor came from the high moon, which was peering down through the
smoke hole in the roof. There was a growling sound outside, and a noise as
of some great animal scuffling at the door. Bilbo wondered what it was, and
whether it could be Bejorn an enchanted shape, and if he would come in as a bear
and kill them. He dived under the blankets and hid his head, and fell
asleep again at last, in spite of his fears. It was full morning when he
awoke. One of the dwarves had fallen over him in the shadows where he lay,
and had rolled down with a bump from the platform onto the floor. It was Bofur,
and he was grumbling about it when Bilbo opened his eyes.
Get up, lazy bones, he said, or there will be no breakfast left for you. Up
jumped Bilbo. Breakfast, he cried. Where is breakfast?
Mostly inside us, answered the other dwarves, who were moving about the hall,
but what is left is out on the veranda.
We have been about looking for Bejorn ever since the sun got up, but there is
no sign of him anywhere, though we found breakfast laid as soon as we went out.
Where is Gandalf? asked Bilbo, moving off to find something to eat as quick as
he could. Oh, out and about somewhere, they told him. But he saw no sign of the
wizard all that day until the evening.
Just before sunset he walked into the hall where the hobbit and the dwarves
were having supper, waited on by Beerren's wonderful animals, as they had
been all day. of Beorin. They had seen and heard nothing since the night
before, and they were getting puzzled.
"Where is our host, and where have you been all day yourself?" they all cried.
"One question at a time, and none till after supper. I haven't had a bite since breakfast."
At last Gandalf pushed away his plate in jug he had eaten two whole loaves with
masses of butter and honey and clotted cream and drunk at least a quart of mead
and he took out his pipe. I will answer the second question first, he said, but
bless me. This is a splendid place for smoke rings. Indeed, for a long time
they could get nothing more out of him.
He was so busy sending smoke rings, dodging round the pillars of the hall,
changing them into all sorts of different shapes and colors, and sending
them at last chasing one another out of the hole in the roof. They must have
looked very queer from outside, popping out into the air one after another.
green, blue, red, silver, gray, yellow, white, bake ones, little ones, little
ones dodging through big ones and joining into figure8s and going off like
a flock of birds into the distance.
"I've been picking out bear tracks," he said at last. "There must have been a
regular bears meeting outside here last night. I soon saw that Bejorn could not
have made them all. There were far too many of them, and they were of various
sizes, too. I should say there were little bears, large bears, ordinary
bears, and gigantic big bears, all dancing outside from dark to nearly
dawn. They came from almost every direction except from the west over the
river, from the mountains. In that direction only one set of footprints led
none coming, only ones going away from here. I followed these as far as the
car. There they disappeared into the river, but the water was too deep and
strong beyond the rock for me to cross.
It is easy enough, as you remember, to get from this bank to the Kok by the
fort, but on the other side is a cliff standing up from a swirling channel. I
had to walk miles before I found a place where the river was wide and shallow
enough for me to wade and swim, and then miles back again to pick up the tracks
again. By that time, it was too late for me to follow them far. They went
straight off in the direction of the pinewoods on the east side of the Misty
Mountains, where we had our pleasant little party with the wards the night
before last. "And now I think I have answered your first question, too,"
ended Gandalf, and he sat a long while silent. Bilbo thought he knew what the
wizard meant. "What shall we do?" he cried. "If he leads all the wards and
the goblins down here, we shall all be caught and killed. I thought you said he
was not a friend of theirs.
So I did. And don't be silly. You had better go to bed. Your wits are sleepy.
The hobbit felt quite crushed. And as there seemed nothing else to do, he did
go to bed. And while the dwarves were still singing songs, he dropped asleep,
still puzzling his little head about Bejorn, till he dreamed a dream of
hundreds of black bears dancing slow, heavy dances round and round in the
moonlight in the courtyard. Then he woke up when everyone else was asleep, and he
heard the same scraping, scuffling, snuffling, and growling as before.
Next morning they were all wakened by Bjorn himself. "So here you all are
still," he said. He picked up the hobbit and laughed. Not eaten up by wards or
goblins or wicked bears yet, I see. And he poked Mr. Baggin's waste coat most
disrespectfully. "Little Bunny is getting nice and fat again on bread and
honey," he chuckled. "Come and have some more." So they all went to breakfast
with him. "Bear was most charlie for a change. Indeed, he seemed to be in a
splendidly good humor, and set them all laughing with his funny stories. nor did
they have to wonder long where he had been or why he was so nice to them, for
he told them himself. He had been over the river and right back up into the
mountains, from which you can guess that he could travel quickly in bare shape at
any rate. From the burnt wolf glade he had soon found out that part of their
story was true, but he had found more than that. He had caught a ward in a
goblin wandering in the woods. From these he had got news. The goblin
patrols were still hunting with wargs for the dwarves, and they were fiercely
angry because of the death of the great goblin, and also because of the burning
of the chief wolf's nose, and the death from the wizards fire of many of his
chief servants. So much they told him when he forced them. But he guessed
there was more wickedness than this a foot, and that a great raid of the whole
goblin army with their wolf alleys into the lands shadowed by the mountains
might soon be made to find the dwarves, or to take vengeance on the men and
creatures that lived there, and who they thought must be sheltering them. "It was
a good story, that of yours," said Bejorn, "but I like it still better now.
I am sure it is true. Ye must forgive my not taking your word. If you lived near
the edge of Murkwood, you would take the word of no one that you did not know as
well as your brother or better. As it is, I can only say that I have hurried
home as fast as I could to see that you were safe, and to offer you any help
that I can loan. I shall think more kindly of dwarves after this. Killed the
great goblin, killed the great goblin, he chuckled fiercely to himself. What
did you do with the goblin and the ward?
asked Bilbo suddenly. Come and see, said Beerren, and they followed round the
house. A goblin's head was stuck outside the gate, and a ward skin was nailed to
a tree just beyond. Beer was a fierce enemy, but now he was their friend, and
Gandalf thought it wise to tell him their whole story and the reason of
their journey so that they could get the most help he could offer. This is what
he promised to do for them. He would provide ponies for each of them and a
horse for Gandalf for their journey to the forest. And he would laid them with
food to last them for weeks with care, and packs so as to be as easy as
possible to carry nuts, flour, sealed jars of dried fruits, and red earthnware
pots of honey, and twice baked cakes that would keep good a long time, and on
a little of which they could march far.
The making of these was one of his secrets. But honey was in them, as in
most of his foods, and they were good to eat, though they made one thirsty.
Water, he said, they would not need to carry this side of the forest, for there
were streams and springs along the road.
But your way through Murkwood is dark, dangerous, and difficult, he said. Water
is not easy to find there, nor food. The time is not yet come for nuts, though it
may be passed and gone indeed before you get to the other side, and nuts are
about all that grows there fit for food.
In there the wild things are dark, queer, and savage. I will provide you
with skins for carrying water, and I will give you some bows and arrows. But
I doubt very much whether anything you find in Merkwood will be wholesome to
eat or to drink. There is one stream there I know, black and strong, which
crosses the path, that you should neither drink of nor bathe in. For I
have heard that it carries enchantment and a great drowsiness and forgetfulness.
And in the dim shadows of that place, I don't think you will shoot anything,
wholesome or unh wholesome, without straying from the path that you must not
do for any reason. That is all the advice I can give you. Beyond the edge
of the forest, I cannot help you much.
You must depend on your luck and your courage and the food I send with you. At
the gate of the forest, I must ask you to send back my horse and my ponies. But
I wish you all speed, and my house is open to you, if ever you come back this
way again. They thanked him, of course, with many bows and sweepings of their
hoods, and with many and at your service, O master of the wide wooden
holes. But their spirits sank at his grave words, and they all felt that the
adventure was far more dangerous than they had thought. While all the time,
even if they passed all the perils of the road, the dragon was waiting at the
end. All that morning they were busy with preparations. Soon after midday
they ate with beer for the last time, and after the meal they mounted the
steeds he was lending them, and bidding him many farewells they rode off through
his gate at a good pace. As soon as they
left his high hedges at the east of his fenced lands, they turned north and then
bore to the northwest. By his advice, they were no longer making for the main
forest road to the south of his land.
Had they followed the path, their path would have led them down a stream from
the mountains that joined the great river miles south of the Karak. At that
point there was a deep ford which they might have passed if they had still had
their ponies, and beyond that a track led to the skirts of the wood and to the
entrance of the old forest road. But Bejorn had warned them that that way was
now often used by the goblins, while the forest road itself, he had heard, was
overgrown and disused at the eastern end, and led to impassible marshes,
where the paths had long been lost. Its eastern opening had also always been far
to the south of the lonely mountain, and would have left them still with a long
and difficult northward march when they got to the other side. North of the
Kerac the edge of Murkwood drew closer to the borders of the great river. And
though here the mountains too drew down nearer, Bejorn advised them to take this
way. For at a place a few days ride due
north of the Kok was the gate of a little known pathway through Murkwood
that led almost straight towards the lonely mountain. The goblins, Bejorn had
said, will not dare to cross the great river for a 100 miles north of the
Carrick, nor to come near my house, it is well protected at night. But I should
ride fast, for if they make their raid soon, they will cross the river to the
south and scour all the edge of the forest, so as to cut you off, and ward
run swifter than ponies. Still, you are safer going north, even though you seem
to be going back nearer to their strongholds, for that is what they will
least expect, and they will have a longer ride to catch you. Be off now as
quick as you may. That is why they were now riding in silence, galloping
wherever the ground was grassy and smooth, with the mountains dark on their
left, and in the distance the line of the river with its trees drawing ever
closer. The sun had only just turned west when they started, until evening it
lay golden on the land about them. It was difficult to think of pursuing
goblins behind, and when they had put many miles between them in Beerren's
house, they began to talk and to sing again, and to forget the dark forest
path that lay in front. But in the evening, when the dusk came on, and the
peaks of the mountains glowered against the sunset, they made a cap and set a
guard, and most of them slept uneasily with dreams, in which there came the
howl of hunting wolves, and the cries of goblins.
Still the next morning dawned bright and fair again. There was an autumnike mist
white upon the ground, and the air was chill. But soon the sun rose red in the
east, and the mists vanished. And while the shadows were still long, they were
off again. So they rode now for two more days. And all the while they saw nothing
save grass and flowers and birds and scattered trees, and occasionally small
herds of red deer browsing or sitting at noon in the shade. Sometimes Bilbo saw
the horns of the height sticking up out of the long grass, and at first he
thought they were the dead branches of trees. That third evening they were so
eager to press on, for Bjornne had said that they should reach the forest gate
early on the fourth day that they rode still forward after dusk and into the
night beneath the moon. As the light faded, Bilbo thought he saw a way to the
right or to the left the shadowy form of a great bear prowling along in the same
direction. But if he dared to mention it to Gandalf, the wizard only said, "Hush,
take no notice."
Next day they started before dawn, though their night had been short. As
soon as it was light, they could see the forest coming, as it were, to meet them,
or waiting for them like a black and frowning wall before them. The land
began to slope up and up, and it seemed to the hobbit that a silence began to
draw in upon them.
Birds began to sing less. There were no more deer. Not even rabbits were to be
seen. By the afternoon they had reached the eaves of Murkwood and were resting
almost beneath the great overhanging boughs of its outer trees. Their trunks
were huge and gnarled. Their branches twisted. Their leaves were dark and
long. Ivy grew on them and trailed along the ground. "Well, here is Mirkwood,"
said Gandalf. the greatest of the forests of the northern world. I hope
you like the look of it. Now you must send back these excellent ponies you
have borrowed. The dwarves were inclined to grumble at this, but the wizard told
them they were fools. Beorn is not as far off as you seem to think, and you
had better keep your promises anyway, for he is a bad enemy. Mr. Baggins eyes
are sharper than yours. If you have not seen each night after dark, a great bear
going along with us, or sitting far off in the moon watching our camps, not only
to guard you and guide you, but to keep an eye on the ponies, too. Beern may be
your friend, but he loves his animals as his children. You do not guess what
kindness he has shown you in letting dwarves ride them so far and so fast,
nor what would happen to you if he tried to take them into the forest.
What about the horse then? said Thoren.
You don't mention sending that back. I don't because I am not sending it. What
about your promise then? I will look after that. I am not sending the horse
back. I am riding it. Then they knew that Gandalf was going to leave them at
the very edge of Murkwood, and they were in despair.
But nothing they could say would change his mind. Now we had this all out before
when we landed on the Kok. He said it is
no use arguing. I have, as I told you, some pressing business away south, and I
am already late through bothering with you people. We may meet again before all
is over, and then again, of course, we may not. That depends on your luck and
on your courage and sense, and I am sending Mr. Baggins with you. I have
told you before that he has more about him than you guess, and you will find
that out before long. So, cheer up, Bilbo, and don't look so glum. Cheer up
Thoren and company. This is your expedition after all. Think of the
treasure at the end, and forget the forest and the dragon at any rate until
tomorrow morning." When tomorrow morning came, he still said the same. So now
there was nothing left to do but to fill their water skins at a clear spring they
found close to the forest gate and unpacked the ponies. They distributed
the packages as fairly as they could, though Bilbo thought his lot was
weariously heavy and did not at all like the idea of trudging for miles and miles
with all that on his back. Don't you worry, said Thorin. It will get lighter
all too soon. Before long, I expect we shall all wish our packs heavier when
the food begins to run short. Then, at last they said goodbye to their ponies,
and turned their heads for home. Off they trotted gay, seeming very glad to
put their tails towards the shadow of Murkwood.
As they went away, Bilbo could have sworn that a thing like a bear left the
shadow of the trees, and shambled off quickly after them. Now, Gandalf too
said farewell. Bilbo sat on the ground feeling very unhappy and wishing he was
beside the wizard on his tall horse. He had gone just inside the forest after
breakfast, a very poor one, and it had seemed as dark in there in the morning
as at night, and very secret, a sort of watching and waiting feeling, he said to
himself. "Goodbye," said Gandalf to Thoren. "And goodbye to you all.
Goodbye. Straight through the forest is your way now. Don't stray off the track.
If you do, it is a thousand to one. You will never find it again, and never get
out of Mirkwood, and then I don't suppose I or anyone else will ever see
you again. Do we really have to go through? Grown the Hobbit.
Yes, you do, said the wizard. If you want to get to the other side, you must
either go through or give up your quest.
And I am not going to allow you to back out now, Mr. Baggins. I am ashamed of
you for thinking of it. You have got to look after all these dwarves for me. He laughed.
No, no, said Do. I didn't mean that. I meant is there no way round. There is.
If you care to go 200 m or so out of
your way north and twice that south, but you wouldn't get a safe path even then.
There are no safe paths in this part of the world. Remember, you are over the
edge of the wild now and in for all sorts of fun wherever you go. Before you
could get round Murkwood in the north, you would be right among the slopes of
the Grey Mountains, and they are simply stiff with goblins, hobgoblins, and orcs
of the worst description.
Before you could get rounded in the south, you would get into the land of
the necromancer. And even you, Bilbo, won't need me to tell you tales of that
black sorcerer. I don't advise you to go anywhere near the places overlooked by
his dark tower. Stick to the forest track. Keep your spirits up, hope for
the best, and with a tremendous slice of luck, you may come out one day and see
the long marshes lying below you and beyond them high in the east, the lonely
mountain where dear old Smau lives, though I hope he is not expecting you.
Very comforting you are to be sure, growled Saurin. Goodbye. If you won't
come with us, you had better get off without any more talk. Goodbye then, and
really goodbye, said Gandalf, and he turned his horse and rode down into the
west. But he could not resist the temptation to have the last word. Before
he had passed quite out of hearing, he turned and put his hands to his mouth
and called to them. They heard his voice come faintly, goodbye. Be good. Take
care of yourselves and dot leave the path. Then he galloped away and was soon
lost to sight. Oh, goodbye and go away, grunted the dwarves, all the more angry,
because they were really filled with dismay at losing him. Now began the most
dangerous part of all the journey. They each shouldered the heavy pack and the
water skin which was their share, and turned from the light that lay on the
lands outside, and plunged into the